Guide to the Frank Cousins Photographs, 1891-1901
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Frank Cousins photographs 1891-1901
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Cousins, Frank
1.0 Linear Feet 220 Items
Salem (Essex Co.), Mass., writer and photographer, specializing in colonial American architecture.
Collection contains photographs that Cousins made; the vast majority of them were taken of Salem, Mass. They are albumen prints, most in good or excellent condition. The subjects are primarily houses, churches, and public buildings of Salem, exterior and interior shots.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Frank Cousins Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift.
Biographical Note
Frank Cousins was a Salem (Essex Co.), Mass. writer and photographer, specializing in colonial American architecture.
Collection Overview
Collection contains photographs that Cousins made; the vast majority of them were taken of Salem, Mass. They are albumen prints, most in good or excellent condition. The subjects are primarily houses, churches, and public buildings of Salem, exterior and interior shots.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Cousins, Frank
Documentary photography -- United States
Architecture -- Massachusetts -- Salem
Historic buildings -- Massachusetts -- Salem
Albumen prints
Contents of Collection
- Frank Cousins Photographs, 1891-1901, (1 box)
  Collection contains photographs from albums Cousins made entitled Views of Historic Salem. Photographs are albumen prints, most in good or excellent condition. The subjects are primarily houses, churches, and public buildings of Salem, exterior and interior shots.
  - Market House and Town Hall, 1891, Print 2 (Box 1)
  - First Church (Unitarian), Essex Corner of Washington St., Print 4
  - Naumkeag Steam Cotton Co. Mills, Print 6
  - Old Witch House, Corner Essex and North Sts., Print 7
  - Hawthorne's Birthplace, 27 Union St., Print 9
  - Court Houses, Corner of Washington and Federal Sts., Print 10
  - Post Office, Print 12
  - Custom House and Old Ladies' Home, Print 14
  - Salem Hospital, 31 Charter St., Print 17
  - Plummer Hall, 134 Essex St., 1891, Print 18
  - North Church (Unitarian), Essex St., 1891, Print 20
  - East Church (Unitarian), Washington Sq. between Brown and Williams Sts., Print 23
  - Church of the Immaculate Conception, Print 24
  - East Church (Unitarian), Print 25
  - St. Peter's Church (Episcopal), Print 26
  - Advent Christian Church, Erected 1890, Print 28
  - Narbonne House, 71 Essex St., Print 30
  - Dr. Grimshaw House, 53 Charter St., 1891 (where Hawthorne Did His Courting, 1838-1840), Print 31
  - Safford House, 1891, Print 33
  - Public Library, 1891, Print 34
  - First Church in Salem, Erected 1634, in 1891, Print 36
  - Bertram House for Aged Men, 70 Derby St., Print 39
  - Tabernacle Church (Congregational), Print 40
  - John Ward House, Print 42
  - Old Bakery, 21 Washington St., Print 43
  - John Derby Mansion, 70 Washington St., Print 45
  - Peabody Mansion, 29 Washington Sq. Now (1898) Horne of Salem Club, Print 87
  - Custom House, Naval Officers' Room, Showing Hawthorne's Room, 1891, Print 89
  - Wesley Church (Methodist), 1891, Print 91
  - Judge Story House, Print 92
  - State Normal School, Corner Broad and Summer Sts., Now (in 1901) an Annex to High School, Print 96
  - Old Sun Tavern, 26 English St., Print 100
  - Universalist Church, Rust St., Print 101
  - Allen House, 77 Derby St., Print 102
  - Samuel Curwen House, 312 Essex St., Birthplace of Author Maria Susanna Cummins, Print 103
  - New Salem Court House (1891), Law Library, Print 104
  - New Salem Court House, Law Library, Print 105
  - New Salem Court House, Law Library, Print 106
  - New Salem Court House, Law Library, Print 107
  - A. C. Goodell's House, Site of Old Witchcraft Jail, Print 108
  - Central Fire Station, 30 Church St., Print 114
  - Hon. Rufus Choate House, 14 Lynde St., 1891, Print 117
  - Manning House, 26 Dearborn St., Print 118
  - Joseph Cabot House, 365 Essex St., Print 120
  - Forrester House, 120 Derby St., Mantel, Print 128
  - Cadet-Armory Peabody House, 136 Essex St., Print 132
  - Cadet Armory, Battalion Headquarters, 136 Essex St., Print 133
  - Timothy Orne House, 266 Essex St., Print 134
  - Derby Mansion, 140 Lafayette St., Print 135
  - Wheatland House, Print 139
  - Grace Church (Episcopal), Print 140
  - Pineapple House, Print 143
  - Franklin Building, 10 Washington Sq., Print 144
  - Sanders House, 292 Essex St., Print 145
  - Emmerton House, Essex St., Print 148
  - 19 Mangin St., Doorway, Print 157
  - George Cabot House, 104 Cabot St., Beverly, Mass., 1891, Print 160
  - Northey Block, N.W. Corner of Essex and Washington Sts., Print 161
  - Ropes House, 318 Essex St., Print 168
  - Mason House, Charter St., Print 177
  - Old Assembly House, 138 Federal St., Print 180
  - Peabody Academy of Science, Interior of New Hall, 1891, Print 186
  - Peabody Academy of Science, Interior, 1891, Print 189
  - First Baptist Church, Print 191
  - Wesley Church, Interior, Print 192
  - St. Peter's Church (Taken Down in 1833) from Painting by Dr. George Perkins, Print 196
  - Central Baptist Church, Print 198
  - Barton Square Church, Now (in 1901) Remodeled into Salem Theater, Print 199
  - City Hall and Kinsman Block, Print 200
  - Essex House, 176 Essex St., Print 204
  - Benjamin Goodhue House, 70 Boston St., Print 212
  - Essex Institute, Print 219
  - Odd Fellows Hall and Asiatic Building, Print 222
  - Lindall-Gibbs House, 314 Essex St., Print 241
  - Price Block, Corner Essex and Washington Sts., Print 243
  - Lindall-Andrews House, 393 Essex St., 1891, Print 246
  - Old Crowninshield House, Print 247
  - Old Shattuck House, Essex St., Print 248
  - Miles Ward House, Derby St. (Hawthorne Visited Here), Print 249
  - Birthplace of Gen. Lander, Barton Sq., Print 250
  - Nichols House, 80 Federal St., Print 253
  - Pickering House, Broad St., Print 255
  - Essex Institute, Print 256
  - Lindall-Andrews House, 393 Essex St. Stairway, Print 261
  - Colonial Stables, Barn and Sheds on Ocean Ave., Rear of E. Hersey Derby's Mansion, Lafayette St., Print 262
  - Derby Mansion, Lafayette St. Mantel in Parlor, 1891, Print 265
  - Salem Public Library. Interior Delivery Room, Print 272
  - Washington Hall, Interior Fireplace, 1892, Print 278
  - Mrs. Stevenson's Variety Store, 60 Essex St., Now (1898) Taken down, Print 280
  - Stowe Bakery, Derby St., Being Remodeled 1895, Capt. Townsend's Brick House, Print 281
  - Knapp House, 85 ES.sex St., Print 296
  - Dr. Carleton's House, Corner of Lynde and North Sts., Print 298
  - House of Seven Gables, 54 Turner St., Hallway, Print 302
  - House of Seven Gables, Clifford's Chamber, Print 303
  - Nichols House, 80 Federal St., Hallway, Print 307 1/2
  - Nichols House, Hallway, 1891, Print 307B
  - Nichols House, Sitting Room, Print 310
  - Essex Institute, Historic Room, Print 317
  - House, 14 Mall St., (where Hawthorne wrote The Scarlet Letter), Print 323
  - Essex Institute, Secretary's Room, 1891, Print 328
  - First National Bank, 11 Central St., Print 363
  - Ernmerton House, 328 Essex St., Doorway, Print 368
  - Waite House, 376 Essex St., Doorway, Print 369
  - 23 Summer St., Doorway, Print 370
  - 126-128 Bridge St., Double Doorway, Print 371
  - Wheatland House, 374 Essex St., Doorway, Print 373
  - Essex Institute, Doorway, 1891, Print 374
  - Whipple House, 2 Andover St., Dutch Door, 1891, Print 375
  - Cabot-Endicott House, 365 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 376
  - 129 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 377
  - Meek House, 81 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 378
  - 92 Washington Sq. East, Doorway, 1891, Print 379
  - Silsbee House, 85 Washington Sq., Doorway, 1891, Print 380
  - Knapp House, 85 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 381
  - 269 Essex St., Doorway, Print 382
  - Public Library, Doorway, Print 383
  - Wilson House, 28 C4estnut St., Doorway, Print 384
  - White House, 128 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 385
  - Curwen Gillis House, 331-332 Essex St., Doorways, Print 386
  - Bowden House, 82 Pleasant St., Now (in 1901) Washington Sq. East, Doorway, Print 387
  - Lord House, Doorway, Corner of Washington Sq. and Oliver St., Print 388
  - 314 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 389
  - Old Devereux House, 72 Washington Sq., Doorway, Print 390
  - Whipple House, 2 Andover St., Dutch Doorway, Print 391
  - Lee House, 14 Chestnut St., Doorway, 1891, Print 392
  - Kimball, Nichols House, 2-4 Brown St., Double Doorway, Print 393
  - Dr. Grimshaw House, Home of Dr. Peabody, 53 Charter St., Doorway (where Hawthorne met Sophia Peapody), Print 394
  - Salem Cadet Armory (Old Residence of Francis Peabody), 136 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 395
  - Lord House, 31 Washington Sq., Doorway, 1891, Print 396
  - Ropes House, 318 Essex St., Doorway, Print 397
  - Peabody Mansion, 1891, Now (in 1901) the Salem Club, Doorway, Print 398
  - Peabody Mansion, 1891, Now (in 1901) the Salem Club, Doorway, Print 398
  - W. H. Silsbee House, 380 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 399
  - W. H. Silsbee House, 380 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 399
  - 103 Essex St., Doorway, Print 400
  - Webb House, 53 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 401
  - Stearns House, 384 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 402
  - Judge Osgood's Residence (1891), 312 Essex St., Doorway., Print 403
  - 118 Derby St., Doorway, Print 404
  - Old Man's Home, 20 Turner St., Doorway, Print 405
  - Goldthwaite House, 20 Turner St., Now (in 1901) Bertram's Home for Aged Men, 1891, Print 405
  - Pineapple House, 7 Brown St., doorway, Print 406
  - Safford House, 13 Washington Sq. West, Doorway, Print 407
  - Brown House, 40 Summer St., Doorway, Print 409
  - House on Corner of Boardman St. and Washington Sq. East, Doorway, Print 410
  - 25 Lynde St., Doorway, Print 411
  - Ward House, 27 Herbert, Doorway, 1891, Print 412
  - Bertram House (Nov. 1891, occupied by widow of John Bertram), formerly Old Assembly House, Doorway, Print 413
  - Williams House, 5 Monroe St., Doorway, Print 414
  - 27 North St., Doorway, 1891, Print 415
  - Nichols House, Colonial Window, 1891, Print 416
  - Nichols House, 80 Federal St., Doorway, 1891, Print 417
  - Emmerton House, 328 Essex St., Doorway, Print 418
  - Shreves Horne, 27 Chestnut St., Doorway, 1891, Print 419
  - Skinner House, 9 Federal St., Doorway, 1891, Print 420
  - 9 Downing St., Doorway, 1891, Print 421
  - Little House, 10 Chestnut St., Doorway, 1891, Print 422
  - 134 Bridge St. Doorway, Print 423
  - West House, 12 Chestnut St., Doorway, 1891, Print 424
  - Dr. Shreve's House, 29 Chestnut St., Doorway, Print 425
  - 359 Essex St., Doorway, 1891, Print 426
  - Simon Forrester House, 120 Derby St., Doorway, 1891, Print 427
  - Old Ladies Home, 114 Derby St., Mantel in Parlor, Print 429
  - Old Ladies' Home, Parlor, 1891, Print 430
  - Lindall House, 393 Essex St., Chamber Mantel, 1891, Print 432
  - 48 Charter St., Newel Post in Stairway in Front Hall, 1891, Print 434
  - Timothy Orne House, 266 Essex St., Main Stairway Landing and Return, 1891, Print 435
  - Timothy Orne or Hodges House, 266 Essex St., Lower, Section of Stairway with Newel Principle Post at Foot, 1891, Print 436
  - Cadet Armory, Inside Doorway, Print 438
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Parlor, 1891, Print 439
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Marble Mantel in Parlor, 1891, Print 440
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Fireplace and Mantel in English Oak Banquet Hall, 1891, Print 441
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Cathedral Window in Banquet Hall, 1891, Print 442
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Folding Doorway in Parlor, 1891, Print 443
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Veteran's Room, 1891, Print 445
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Mantel in Battalion Headquarters, Print 446
  - Salem Cadet Armory, N.C.O. Room, Looking North, 1891, Print 447
  - Salem Cadet Armory, N.C.O. Room, Looking West, 1891, Print 448
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Parlor, Looking North, 1891, Print 449
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Parlor, Looking South, 1891, Print 450
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Veterans Room, Print 451
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Library, 1st Floor, Print 452
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Parlor, 1891, Print 453
  - Queen Hotel, 37 Lathrop St., Beverly, Mass., Ladies Parlor, Destroyed by Fire, Nov. 24, 1891, Print 454
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Billiard Hall, Western End, Print 455
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Billiard Hall, Eastern End, Print 456
  - Old Courthouse, Probate Court, Print 458
  - Lee House, Chestnut St., 1891, Print 464
  - Narbonne House, 71 Essex St., Front Room, Print 501
  - Narbonne House, Front Room Showing Beam in Ceiling, 1891, Print 502
  - Queen Hotel, 37 Lathrop St., Beverly, Mass., 1891, Destroyed by Fire Later, Print 568
  - Queen Hotel, Dining Room, Print 570
  - Salem Cadet Armory, Battalion Headquarters, 1891, Print 571
  - 14 Mall St., 1891 (Hawthorne's Study Where He Wrote The Scarlet Letter), Print 583
  - The Wayside, Hawthorne's Chamber and Chair, Concord, Mass., 1891, Print 621
  - The Wayside, Library, and Hawthorne's Den and Bookcase, 1891, Print 633
  - Cook House, 142 Federal St., Doorway, 1891, Print 652
  - Waters House, 80 Washington Sq. East, Print 659
  - Drawing Room in House in S. Salem, Print 663
  - John Ward House, 38 St. Peter St., Now 1901 Standing, Print 666
  - Waters House, Doorway, 1891, Print 672
  - 14 Pickman St., Doorway, 1891, Print 676
  - 25 Federal St., Doorway, 1891, Print 681
  - Crowninshield-Devereux House, Doorway Interior, 1891, Print 682
  - Crowninshield-Devereux House, 1891, Print 684
  - Crowninshie1d-Devereux, House, South Front, Print 685
  - Women's Bureau, 12 Elm St., Mantel in Parlor, Print 686
  - Col. Page House, Elm St., Danvers, Mass., Room with Fireplace, 1891, Print 687
  - Crowninshield-Devereux House, Pier Table, 1891, Print 688
  - Brown House, 40 Summer St., Stairway and Lower Hall with Samuel McIntire Rail, 1891, Print 691
  - Brown House, Upper Hall and Stairway, 1891, Print 692
  - Brown House, Stairway and Upper Landing, 1891, Print 693
  - Kimball House, 14 Pickman St., Mantel and Fireplace, 1891, Print 694
  - Kimball House, Mantel and Fireplace, 1891, Print 696
  - Courthouses, 1891, Print 699
  - Woman's Bureau, 12 Elm St., Mantel in Rear Room, Print 701
  - Woman's Bureau, 12 Elm St., Mantel with Candelabra, Print 729
  - Crowninshield-Devereux House, Parlor with Mantel, 1891, Print 732
  - Pickering House, 91 Lathrop St., Beverly, Mass., Print 738
  - H. W. Pickering House, Beverly, Mass., Rear View, Print 739